Why is this man smiling?
The Unknown Known is a documentary, history film directed by Errol Morris.
Former United States Secretary of Defense, Donald
Rumsfeld, discusses his career in Washington D.C.
from his days as a congressman in the early 1960s to
planning the invasion of Iraq in 2003.
Self, played by Donald Rumsfeld.
Younger Donald Rumsfeld / Secret Service, played by Kenn Medeiros.
Self - Interviewer (voice), played by Errol Morris.
"There are unknown unknowns" is a phrase from a response United States
Secretary of Defense Donald Rumsfeld gave to a question at a U.S.
Department of Defense (DoD) news briefing on February 12, 2002, about the lack of evidence linking the
government of Iraq with the supply of weapons of mass destruction to terrorist groups.
Rumsfeld stated:
Reports that say that something hasn't happened are always interesting to me,
because as we know, there are known knowns; there are things we know we know.
We also know there are known unknowns; that is to say we
know there are some things we do not know.
But there are also unknown unknowns—the ones we don't know we don't know.
And if one looks throughout the history of our country and other free countries,
it is the latter category that tends to be the difficult ones.
The statement became the subject of much commentary.
In The Decision Book (2013), author Mikael Krogerus
refers to it as the "Rumsfeld matrix".
The statement also features in a 2013 documentary film, The
Unknown Known, directed by Errol Morris.
Known unknowns refers to "risks you are aware of, such as canceled flights", whereas unknown unknowns are
risks that come from situations that are so unexpected that they would not be considered.